<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<mediawiki xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <page>
    <title>Stem cell</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>27783</id>
    <revision>
      <id>794580567</id>
      <parentid>794066419</parentid>
      <timestamp>2017-08-08T21:06:18Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Bender the Bot</username>
        <id>28903366</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor></minor>
      <comment>/* Embryonic */Repairing broken [[Wall Street Journal]] links using [[Project:AWB|AWB]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{About|the cell type|the medical therapy|Stem cell therapy}}
{{pp-move-indef|small=yes}}
{{Infobox anatomy
| Name        = Stem cell
| Latin       = Cellula praecursoria
| GraySubject = 
| GrayPage    = 
| Image       = MSC high magnification.jpg
| Caption     = [[Transmission electron microscopy|Transmission]] [[electron micrograph]] of an adult stem cell displaying typical [[Ultrastructure|ultrastructural]] characteristics.
| Width       = 
| Image2      = 
| Caption2    = 
| ImageMap    = 
| MapCaption  = 
| Precursor   = 
| System      = 
| Artery      = 
| Vein        = 
| Nerve       = 
| Lymph       = 
| MeshName    = 
| MeshNumber  = 
| Code        = [[Terminologia Histologica|TH]] H2.00.01.0.00001
| Dorlands    = 
| DorlandsID  = 
}}
'''Stem cells''' are [[Cellular differentiation|undifferentiated]] [[cell (biology)|biological cells]] that can [[Cellular differentiation|differentiate]] into specialized cells and can [[cell division|divide]] (through [[mitosis]]) to produce more stem cells. They are found in multicellular [[organisms]]. In [[mammal]]s, there are two broad types of stem cells: [[embryonic stem cell]]s, which are isolated from the [[inner cell mass]] of [[blastocyst]]s, and [[adult stem cell]]s, which are found in various [[tissue (biology)|tissue]]s. In [[adult]] organisms, stem cells and [[progenitor cell]]s act as a repair system for the body, replenishing adult tissues. In a developing [[embryo]], stem cells can differentiate into all the specialized cells—ectoderm, endoderm and mesoderm (see [[induced pluripotent stem cells]])—but also maintain the normal turnover of regenerative organs, such as blood, skin, or intestinal tissues.

There are three known accessible sources of [[autologous]] adult stem cells in humans:
# [[Bone marrow]], which requires extraction by ''harvesting'', that is, drilling into bone (typically the [[femur]] or [[iliac crest]]).
# Adipose tissue (lipid cells), which requires extraction by liposuction.
# Blood, which requires extraction through [[apheresis]], wherein blood is drawn from the donor (similar to a blood donation), and passed through a machine that extracts the stem cells and returns other portions of the blood to the donor.
Stem cells can also be taken from [[umbilical cord blood]] just after birth. Of all stem cell types, autologous harvesting involves the least risk. By definition, autologous cells are obtained from one's own body, just as one may bank his or her own blood for elective surgical procedures.

Adult stem cells are frequently used in various medical therapies (e.g., [[Hematopoietic stem cell transplantation|bone marrow transplantation]]). Stem cells can now be [[Cell culture|artificially grown]] and transformed (differentiated) into specialized cell types with characteristics consistent with cells of various tissues such as muscles or nerves. Embryonic [[cell line]]s and [[autologous]] embryonic stem cells generated through [[somatic cell nuclear transfer]] or [[Cellular differentiation#Dedifferentiation|dedifferentiation]] have also been proposed as promising candidates for future therapies.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | author = Tuch BE | title = Stem cells – a clinical update | journal = [[Australian Family Physician]] | volume = 35 | issue = 9 | pages = 719–21 | year = 2006 | pmid = 16969445 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Research into stem cells grew out of findings by [[Ernest McCulloch|Ernest A. McCulloch]] and [[James Till|James E. Till]] at the [[University of Toronto]] in the 1960s.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |vauthors=Becker AJ, McCulloch EA, Till JE | title = Cytological demonstration of the clonal nature of spleen colonies derived from transplanted mouse marrow cells | journal = Nature | volume = 197 | issue = 4866 | pages = 452–54 | year = 1963 | pmid = 13970094 | doi = 10.1038/197452a0 | bibcode = 1963Natur.197..452B }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |vauthors=Siminovitch L, Mcculloch EA, Till JE | title = The distribution of colony-forming cells among spleen colonies | journal = Journal of Cellular and Comparative Physiology | volume = 62 | issue = 3 | pages = 327–36 | year = 1963 | pmid = 14086156 | doi = 10.1002/jcp.1030620313 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Properties==
The classical definition of a stem cell requires that it possesses two properties:
*''Self-renewal'': the ability to go through numerous [[cell cycle|cycles]] of [[cell division]] while maintaining the undifferentiated state.
*''Potency'': the capacity to [[Cellular differentiation|differentiate]] into specialized cell types. In the strictest sense, this requires stem cells to be either [[totipotency|totipotent]] or [[pluripotency|pluripotent]]—to be able to give rise to any mature cell type, although [[multipotent]] or [[unipotent cell|unipotent]] [[progenitor cell]]s are sometimes referred to as stem cells. Apart from this it is said that stem cell function is regulated in a feed back mechanism.

===Self-renewal===
Two mechanisms exist to ensure that a stem cell population is maintained:
# [[Asymmetric cell division|Obligatory asymmetric replication]]: a stem cell divides into one mother cell that is identical to the original stem cell, and another daughter cell that is differentiated.
# Stochastic differentiation: when one stem cell develops into two differentiated daughter cells, another stem cell undergoes [[mitosis]] and produces two stem cells identical to the original.

===Potency definition===
{{Main article|Cell potency}}
[[Image:Stem cells diagram.png|400px|thumb|right|Pluripotent, embryonic stem cells originate as inner cell mass (ICM) cells within a blastocyst. These stem cells can become any tissue in the body, excluding a placenta. Only cells from an earlier stage of the embryo, known as the [[morula]], are totipotent, able to become all tissues in the body and the extraembryonic placenta.]]
[[Image:Human embryonic stem cells.png|thumb|250px|Human [[embryo]]nic stem cells &lt;br /&gt; A: Stem cell colonies that are not yet differentiated. &lt;br /&gt; B: [[Nerve]] cells, an example of a [[cell type]] after differentiation.]]

''Potency'' specifies the differentiation potential (the potential to differentiate into different cell types) of the stem cell.&lt;ref name=Schoeler&gt;{{cite book |title=Humanbiotechnology as Social Challenge |editor1=Nikolaus Knoepffler |editor2=Dagmar Schipanski |editor3=Stefan Lorenz Sorgner |page=28 |chapter=The Potential of Stem Cells: An Inventory |author=Schöler, Hans R. |publisher=Ashgate Publishing|year=2007 |isbn=978-0-7546-5755-2}}&lt;/ref&gt;

*[[Totipotency|Totipotent]] (a.k.a. omnipotent) stem cells can differentiate into embryonic and extraembryonic cell types. Such cells can construct a complete, viable organism.&lt;ref name=Schoeler/&gt; These cells are produced from the [[Cell fusion|fusion]] of an egg and sperm cell. Cells produced by the first few divisions of the fertilized egg are also totipotent.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |vauthors=Mitalipov S, Wolf D | title = Totipotency, pluripotency and nuclear reprogramming | journal = Adv. Biochem. Eng. Biotechnol. | volume = 114 | pages = 185–99 | year = 2009 | pmid = 19343304 | pmc = 2752493 | doi = 10.1007/10_2008_45 | isbn = 978-3-540-88805-5 | series = Advances in Biochemical Engineering/Biotechnology | bibcode = 2009esc..book..185M }}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Pluripotency|Pluripotent]] stem cells are the descendants of totipotent cells and can differentiate into nearly all cells,&lt;ref name=Schoeler/&gt; i.e. cells derived from any of the three [[germ layer]]s.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |vauthors=Ulloa-Montoya F, Verfaillie CM, Hu WS | title = Culture systems for pluripotent stem cells | journal = J Biosci Bioeng | volume = 100 | issue = 1 | pages = 12–27 | year = 2005 | pmid = 16233846 | doi = 10.1263/jbb.100.12 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Multipotency|Multipotent]] stem cells can differentiate into a number of cell types, but only those of a closely related family of cells.&lt;ref name=Schoeler/&gt;
*[[Oligopotency|Oligopotent]] stem cells can differentiate into only a few cell types, such as lymphoid or myeloid stem cells.&lt;ref name=Schoeler/&gt;
*[[Unipotency|Unipotent]] cells can produce only one cell type, their own,&lt;ref name=Schoeler/&gt; but have the property of self-renewal, which distinguishes them from non-stem cells (e.g. [[progenitor cell]]s, which cannot self-renew).

===Identification===
In practice, stem cells are identified by whether they can regenerate tissue. For example, the defining test for bone marrow or [[hematopoietic stem cell]]s (HSCs) is the ability to transplant the cells and save an individual without HSCs. This demonstrates that the cells can produce new blood cells over a long term. It should also be possible to isolate stem cells from the transplanted individual, which can themselves be transplanted into another individual without HSCs, demonstrating that the stem cell was able to self-renew.

Properties of stem cells can be illustrated ''[[in vitro]]'', using methods such as [[clonogenic assay]]s, in which single cells are assessed for their ability to differentiate and self-renew.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |vauthors=Friedenstein AJ, Deriglasova UF, Kulagina NN, Panasuk AF, Rudakowa SF, Luriá EA, Ruadkow IA | title = Precursors for fibroblasts in different populations of hematopoietic cells as detected by the ''in vitro'' colony assay method | journal = [[Experimental Hematology]] | volume = 2 | issue = 2 | pages = 83–92 | year = 1974 | pmid = 4455512 | issn = 0301-472X }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite journal |vauthors=Friedenstein AJ, Gorskaja JF, Kulagina NN | title = Fibroblast precursors in normal and irradiated mouse hematopoietic organs | journal = [[Experimental Hematology]] | volume = 4 | issue = 5 | pages = 267–74 | year = 1976 | pmid = 976387 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Stem cells can also be isolated by their possession of a distinctive set of cell surface markers. However, ''in vitro'' culture conditions can alter the behavior of cells, making it unclear whether the cells shall behave in a similar manner ''[[in vivo]]''. There is considerable debate as to whether some proposed adult cell populations are truly stem cells.{{Citation needed|date=July 2016}}

==Embryonic==
{{Main article|Embryonic stem cell}}

Embryonic stem (ES) cells are the cells of the [[inner cell mass]] of a [[blastocyst]], an early-stage [[embryo]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |vauthors=Thomson JA, Itskovitz-Eldor J, Shapiro SS, Waknitz MA, Swiergiel JJ, Marshall VS, Jones JM | title = Blastocysts Embryonic Stem Cell Lines Derived from Human | journal = Science | volume = 282 | issue = 5391 | pages = 1145–47 | year = 1998 | pmid = 9804556 | doi = 10.1126/science.282.5391.1145 | bibcode = 1998Sci...282.1145T }}&lt;/ref&gt; Human [[embryo]]s reach the [[blastocyst]] stage 4–5 days post [[Human fertilization|fertilization]], at which time they consist of 50–150 cells. ES cells are [[pluripotent]] and give rise during development to all derivatives of the three primary [[germ layer]]s: ectoderm, endoderm and mesoderm. In other words, they can develop into each of the more than 200 cell types of the adult [[human body|body]] when given sufficient and necessary stimulation for a specific cell type. They do not contribute to the extra-embryonic membranes or the [[placenta]].

During embryonic development these inner cell mass cells continuously divide and become more specialized.  For example, a portion of the ectoderm in the dorsal part of the embryo specializes as '[[neurectoderm]]', which will become the future [[central nervous system]].&lt;ref name="Developmental biology"&gt;{{cite book|last1=Gilbert|first1=Scott F.|last2=College|first2=Swarthmore|last3=Helsinki|first3=the University of|title=Developmental biology|date=2014|publisher=Sinauer|location=Sunderland, Mass.|isbn=978-0878939787|edition=Tenth}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Later in development, [[neurulation]] causes the neurectoderm to form the [[neural tube]].  At the neural tube stage, the anterior portion undergoes [[encephalization]] to generate or 'pattern' the basic form of the brain.  At this stage of development, the principal cell type of the CNS is considered a [[neural stem cell]].  These neural stem cells are pluripotent, as they can generate a large diversity of many different neuron types, each with unique gene expression, morphological, and functional characteristics.  The process of generating neurons from stem cells is called [[neurogenesis]].  One prominent example of a neural stem cell is the [[radial glial cell]], so named because it has a distinctive bipolar morphology with highly elongated processes spanning the thickness of the neural tube wall, and because historically it shared some [[glial]] characteristics, most notably the expression of [[glial fibrillary acidic protein]] (GFAP).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Rakic|first1=P|title=Evolution of the neocortex: a perspective from developmental biology|journal=Nature Reviews. Neuroscience|date=October 2009|volume=10|issue=10|pages=724–35|pmid=19763105|pmc=2913577|doi=10.1038/nrn2719}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Noctor|first1=SC|last2=Flint|first2=AC|last3=Weissman|first3=TA|last4=Dammerman|first4=RS|last5=Kriegstein|first5=AR|title=Neurons derived from radial glial cells establish radial units in neocortex.|journal=Nature|date=8 February 2001|volume=409|issue=6821|pages=714–20|pmid=11217860|doi=10.1038/35055553}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The radial glial cell is the primary neural stem cell of the developing [[vertebrate]] CNS, and its cell body resides in the [[ventricular zone]], adjacent to the developing [[ventricular system]].  Neural stem cells are committed to the neuronal lineages ([[neuron]]s, [[astrocyte]]s, and [[oligodendrocyte]]s), and thus their potency is restricted.&lt;ref name="Developmental biology"/&gt;

Nearly all research to date has made use of mouse embryonic stem cells (mES) or human embryonic stem cells (hES) derived from the early inner cell mass.  Both have the essential stem cell characteristics, yet they require very different environments in order to maintain an undifferentiated state. Mouse ES cells are grown on a layer of [[gelatin]] as an [[extracellular matrix]] (for support) and require the presence of [[leukemia inhibitory factor]] (LIF) in serum media. A drug cocktail containing inhibitors to [[GSK3B]] and the [[MAPK/ERK pathway]], called 2i, has also been shown to maintain pluripotency in stem cell culture.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|pmid= 18497825|year= 2008|author1= Ying|first1= Q. L.|title= The ground state of embryonic stem cell self-renewal|journal= Nature|volume= 453|issue= 7194|pages= 519–23|last2= Wray|first2= J|last3= Nichols|first3= J|last4= Batlle-Morera|first4= L|last5= Doble|first5= B|last6= Woodgett|first6= J|last7= Cohen|first7= P|last8= Smith|first8= A|doi= 10.1038/nature06968}}&lt;/ref&gt; Human ES cells are grown on a feeder layer of mouse embryonic [[fibroblasts]] (MEFs) and require the presence of basic fibroblast growth factor (bFGF or FGF-2).&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite web
 |url=http://stemcells.nih.gov/research/NIHresearch/scunit/culture.asp
 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20100106111652/http://stemcells.nih.gov/research/NIHresearch/scunit/culture.asp
 |archivedate=2010-01-06
 |title=Culture of Human Embryonic Stem Cells (hESC)
 |publisher=National Institutes of Health
 |accessdate=2010-03-07
}}&lt;/ref&gt; Without optimal culture conditions or genetic manipulation,&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite journal |vauthors=Chambers I, Colby D, Robertson M, Nichols J, Lee S, Tweedie S, Smith A | title = Functional expression cloning of Nanog, a pluripotency sustaining factor in embryonic stem cells | journal = Cell | volume = 113 | issue = 5 | pages = 643–55 | year = 2003 | pmid = 12787505 | doi = 10.1016/S0092-8674(03)00392-1 }}&lt;/ref&gt; embryonic stem cells will rapidly differentiate.

A human embryonic stem cell is also defined by the expression of several transcription factors and cell surface proteins. The transcription factors [[Oct-4]], [[Nanog]], and [[Sox2]] form the core regulatory network that ensures the suppression of genes that lead to differentiation and the maintenance of pluripotency.&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite journal |vauthors=Boyer LA, Lee TI, Cole MF, Johnstone SE, Levine SS, Zucker JP, Guenther MG, Kumar RM, Murray HL, Jenner RG, Gifford DK, Melton DA, Jaenisch R, Young RA | title = Core transcriptional regulatory circuitry in human embryonic stem cells | journal = Cell | volume = 122 | issue = 6 | pages = 947–56 | year = 2005 | pmid = 16153702 | pmc = 3006442 | doi = 10.1016/j.cell.2005.08.020 }}&lt;/ref&gt;  The cell surface antigens most commonly used to identify hES cells are the glycolipids [[stage specific embryonic antigen 3]] and 4 and the keratan sulfate antigens Tra-1-60 and Tra-1-81. By using human embryonic stem cells to produce specialized cells like nerve cells or heart cells in the lab, scientists can gain access to adult human cells without taking tissue from patients. They can then study these specialized adult cells in detail to try and catch complications of diseases, or to study cells reactions to potentially new drugs.  The molecular definition of a stem cell includes many more proteins and continues to be a topic of research.&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite journal |vauthors=Adewumi O, Aflatoonian B, Ahrlund-Richter L, Amit M, Andrews PW, Beighton G, Bello PA, Benvenisty N, Berry LS, Bevan S, Blum B, Brooking J, Chen KG, Choo AB, Churchill GA, Corbel M, Damjanov I, Draper JS, Dvorak P, Emanuelsson K, Fleck RA, Ford A, Gertow K, Gertsenstein M, Gokhale PJ, Hamilton RS, Hampl A, Healy LE, Hovatta O, Hyllner J, Imreh MP, Itskovitz-Eldor J, Jackson J, Johnson JL, Jones M, Kee K, King BL, Knowles BB, Lako M, Lebrin F, Mallon BS, Manning D, Mayshar Y, McKay RD, Michalska AE, Mikkola M, Mileikovsky M, Minger SL, Moore HD, Mummery CL, Nagy A, Nakatsuji N, O'Brien CM, Oh SK, Olsson C, Otonkoski T, Park KY, Passier R, Patel H, Patel M, Pedersen R, Pera MF, Piekarczyk MS, Pera RA, Reubinoff BE, Robins AJ, Rossant J, Rugg-Gunn P, Schulz TC, Semb H, Sherrer ES, Siemen H, Stacey GN, Stojkovic M, Suemori H, Szatkiewicz J, Turetsky T, Tuuri T, van den Brink S, Vintersten K, Vuoristo S, Ward D, Weaver TA, Young LA, Zhang W | title = Characterization of human embryonic stem cell lines by the International Stem Cell Initiative | journal = Nat. Biotechnol. | volume = 25 | issue = 7 | pages = 803–16 | year = 2007 | pmid = 17572666 | doi = 10.1038/nbt1318 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

There are currently no approved treatments using embryonic stem cells. The first human trial was approved by the US Food and Drug Administration in January 2009.&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite journal | author = Ron Winslow | title = First Embryonic Stem-Cell Trial Gets Approval from the FDA | series = 23 | journal = The Wall Street Journal | url = https://www.wsj.com/articles/SB123268485825709415 | volume = January 2009 | year = 2009 }}&lt;/ref&gt; However, the human trial was not initiated until October 13, 2010 in Atlanta for [[spinal cord injury research]]. On November 14, 2011 the company conducting the trial ([[Geron Corporation]]) announced that it will discontinue further development of its stem cell programs.&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite web
 |url=http://www.sciencedebate.com/science-blog/embryonic-stem-cell-therapy-risk-geron-ends-clinical-trial
|publisher=ScienceDebate.com
 |title=Embryonic Stem Cell Therapy At Risk? Geron Ends Clinical Trial
 |accessdate=2011-12-11
}}&lt;/ref&gt; ES cells, being pluripotent cells, require specific signals for correct differentiation—if injected directly into another body, ES cells will differentiate into many different types of cells, causing a [[teratoma]]. Differentiating ES cells into usable cells while avoiding transplant rejection are just a few of the hurdles that embryonic stem cell researchers still face.&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite journal |vauthors=Wu DC, Boyd AS, Wood KJ | title = Embryonic stem cell transplantation: potential applicability in cell replacement therapy and regenerative medicine | journal = Front Biosci | volume = 12 | issue = 8–12 | pages = 4525–35 | year = 2007 | pmid = 17485394 | doi = 10.2741/2407 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Due to ethical considerations, many nations currently have [[moratorium (law)|moratoria]] or limitations on either human ES cell research or the production of new human ES cell lines. Because of their combined abilities of unlimited expansion and pluripotency, embryonic stem cells remain a theoretically potential source for [[regenerative medicine]] and tissue replacement after injury or disease.

&lt;gallery&gt;
Image:Mouse embryonic stem cells.jpg | [[Mus musculus|Mouse]] [[Mammalian embryogenesis|embryo]]nic stem cells with fluorescent marker
Image:Human embryonic stem cell colony phase.jpg | Human embryonic stem cell colony on mouse embryonic fibroblast feeder layer
&lt;/gallery&gt;

==Fetal==
The primitive stem cells located in the organs of fetuses are referred to as fetal stem cells.&lt;ref name="isbn981-256-126-9"&gt;
{{cite book |editor1=Ariff Bongso |editor2=Eng Hin Lee | title = Stem Cells: From Benchtop to Bedside | chapter = Stem cells: their definition, classification and sources | publisher = World Scientific | year = 2005 | page = 5 | isbn = 981-256-126-9 | oclc = 443407924 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
There are two types of fetal stem cells:

# Fetal proper stem cells come from the tissue of the fetus proper, and are generally obtained after an [[abortion]]. These stem cells are not immortal but have a high level of division and are multipotent.
# Extraembryonic fetal stem cells come from [[extraembryonic membrane]]s, and are generally not distinguished from adult stem cells. These stem cells are acquired after birth, they are not immortal but have a high level of cell division, and are pluripotent.&lt;ref&gt;Moore, K.L., T.V.N. Persaud, and A.G. Torchia. Before We Are Born: Essentials of Embryology and Birth Defects. Philadelphia, PA: Saunders, Elsevier. 2013. Print&lt;/ref&gt;

==Adult==
{{Main article|Adult stem cell}}

[[Image:Stem cell division and differentiation.svg|thumb|Stem cell division and differentiation. A: stem cell; B: progenitor cell; C: differentiated cell; 1: symmetric stem cell division; 2: asymmetric stem cell division; 3: progenitor division; 4: terminal differentiation]]

Adult stem cells, also called [[Somatic (biology)|somatic]] (from Greek σωματικóς, "of the body") stem cells, are stem cells which maintain and repair the tissue in which they are found.&lt;ref&gt;"Stem Cells" Mayo Clinic. Mayo foundation for medical education and research n.d Web. March 23, 2013&lt;/ref&gt; They can be found in children, as well as adults.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |vauthors=Jiang Y, Jahagirdar BN, Reinhardt RL, Schwartz RE, Keene CD, Ortiz-Gonzalez XR, Reyes M, Lenvik T, Lund T, Blackstad M, Du J, Aldrich S, Lisberg A, Low WC, Largaespada DA, Verfaillie CM | title = Pluripotency of mesenchymal stem cells derived from adult marrow | journal = Nature | volume = 418 | issue = 6893 | pages = 41–9 | year = 2002 | pmid = 12077603 | doi = 10.1038/nature00870 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Pluripotent adult stem cells are rare and generally small in number, but they can be found in umbilical cord blood and other tissues.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |vauthors=Ratajczak MZ, Machalinski B, Wojakowski W, Ratajczak J, Kucia M | title = A hypothesis for an embryonic origin of pluripotent Oct-4(+) stem cells in adult bone marrow and other tissues | journal = Leukemia | volume = 21 | issue = 5 | pages = 860–7 | year = 2007 | pmid = 17344915 | doi = 10.1038/sj.leu.2404630 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Bone marrow is a rich source of adult stem cells,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |vauthors=Narasipura SD, Wojciechowski JC, Charles N, Liesveld JL, King MR | title = P-Selectin coated microtube for enrichment of CD34+ hematopoietic stem and progenitor cells from human bone marrow | journal = Clin Chem | volume = 54 | issue = 1 | pages = 77–85 | year = 2008 | pmid = 18024531 | doi = 10.1373/clinchem.2007.089896 }}&lt;/ref&gt; which have been used in treating several conditions including liver cirrhosis,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |vauthors=Terai S, Ishikawa T, Omori K, Aoyama K, Marumoto Y, Urata Y, Yokoyama Y, Uchida K, Yamasaki T, Fujii Y, Okita K, Sakaida I | title = Improved liver function in patients with liver cirrhosis after autologous bone marrow cell infusion therapy | journal = Stem Cells | volume = 24 | issue = 10 | pages = 2292–8 | year = 2006 | pmid = 16778155 | doi = 10.1634/stemcells.2005-0542 }}&lt;/ref&gt; chronic limb ischemia &lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal  |vauthors=Subrammaniyan R, Amalorpavanathan J, Shankar R, etal |title=Application of autologous bone marrow mononuclear cells in six patients with advanced chronic critical limb ischemia as a result of diabetes: our experience |journal=Cytotherapy |volume=13 |issue=8 |pages=993–9 |date=September 2011  |pmid=21671823 |doi=10.3109/14653249.2011.579961}}&lt;/ref&gt; and endstage heart failure.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|url=http://www.pubstemcell.com/monthly/003010700010.htm | author = Madhusankar N | title = Use of Bone Marrow derived Stem Cells in Patients with Cardiovascular Disorders | journal = Journal of Stem Cells and Regenerative Medicine }}&lt;/ref&gt; The quantity of bone marrow stem cells declines with age and is greater in males than females during reproductive years.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |vauthors=Dedeepiya VD, Rao YY, Jayakrishnan GA, Parthiban JK, Baskar S, Manjunath SR, Senthilkumar R, Abraham SJ | title = Index of CD34+ Cells and Mononuclear Cells in the Bone Marrow of Spinal Cord Injury Patients of Different Age Groups: A Comparative Analysis | journal = Bone Marrow Res | volume = 2012 | page = 787414 | year = 2012 | pmid = 22830032 | pmc = 3398573 | doi = 10.1155/2012/787414 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Much adult stem cell research to date has aimed to characterize their potency and self-renewal capabilities.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | author = Gardner RL | title = Stem cells: potency, plasticity and public perception | journal = Journal of Anatomy | volume = 200 | issue = 3 | pages = 277–82 | year = 2002 | pmid = 12033732 | pmc = 1570679 | doi = 10.1046/j.1469-7580.2002.00029.x }}&lt;/ref&gt;   DNA damage accumulates with age in both stem cells and the cells that comprise the stem cell environment.  This accumulation is considered to be responsible, at least in part, for increasing stem cell dysfunction with aging (see [[DNA damage theory of aging]]).&lt;ref name="pmid24576896"&gt;{{cite journal |vauthors=Behrens A, van Deursen JM, Rudolph KL, Schumacher B |title=Impact of genomic damage and ageing on stem cell function |journal=Nat. Cell Biol. |volume=16 |issue=3 |pages=201–7 |year=2014 |pmid=24576896 |pmc=4214082 |doi=10.1038/ncb2928 |url=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Most adult stem cells are lineage-restricted ([[multipotent]]) and are generally referred to by their tissue origin ([[mesenchymal stem cell]], adipose-derived stem cell, [[endothelial stem cell]], [[dental pulp stem cell]], etc.).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |vauthors=Barrilleaux B, Phinney DG, Prockop DJ, O'Connor KC | title = Review: ex vivo engineering of living tissues with adult stem cells | journal = Tissue Eng | volume = 12 | issue = 11 | pages = 3007–19 | year = 2006 | pmid = 17518617 | doi = 10.1089/ten.2006.12.3007 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |vauthors=Gimble JM, Katz AJ, Bunnell BA | title = Adipose-derived stem cells for regenerative medicine | journal = Circ Res | volume = 100 | issue = 9 | pages = 1249–60 | year = 2007 | pmid = 17495232 | doi = 10.1161/01.RES.0000265074.83288.09 }}&lt;/ref&gt;  [[Muse cells]] (multi-lineage differentiating stress enduring cells) are a recently discovered pluripotent stem cell type found in multiple adult tissues, including adipose, dermal fibroblasts, and bone marrow. While rare, muse cells are identifiable by their expression of [[SSEA-3]], a marker for undifferentiated stem cells, and general mesenchymal stem cells markers such as [[CD105]]. When subjected to single cell suspension culture, the cells will generate clusters that are similar to embryoid bodies in morphology as well as gene expression, including canonical pluripotency markers [[Oct4]], [[Sox2]], and [[Nanog]].&lt;ref name=Kuroda&gt;{{cite journal |vauthors=Kuroda Y, Kitada M, Wakao S, Nishikawa K, Tanimura Y, Makinoshima H, Goda M, Akashi H, Inutsuka A, Niwa A, Shigemoto T, Nabeshima Y, Nakahata T, Nabeshima Y, Fujiyoshi Y, Dezawa M |title=Unique multipotent cells in adult human mesenchymal cell populations |journal=Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A |year=2010 |volume=107 |issue=19 |pages=8639–43 |url=http://www.pnas.org/content/early/2010/04/23/0911647107|bibcode=2010PNAS..107.8639K |doi=10.1073/pnas.0911647107|pmid=20421459|pmc=2889306}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Adult stem cell treatments have been successfully used for many years to treat leukemia and related bone/blood cancers through bone marrow transplants.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.ucsfchildrenshospital.org/treatments/leukemia_treatment_options/index.html |title=Bone Marrow Transplant|work=ucsfchildrenshospital.org}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Adult stem cells are also used in veterinary medicine to treat tendon and ligament injuries in horses.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |first=Ed |last=Kane |title=Stem-cell therapy shows promise for horse soft-tissue injury, disease |url=http://veterinarynews.dvm360.com/dvm/Equine+Medicine/Stem-cell-therapy-shows-promise-for-horse-soft-tis/ArticleStandard/Article/detail/515503 |publisher=DVM Newsmagazine |date=2008-05-01 |accessdate=2008-06-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The use of adult stem cells in research and therapy is not as [[Stem cell controversy|controversial]] as the use of [[embryonic stem cell]]s, because the production of adult stem cells does not require the destruction of an [[embryo]]. Additionally, in instances where adult stem cells are obtained from the intended recipient (an [[autograft]]), the risk of rejection is essentially non-existent. Consequently, more US government funding is being provided for adult stem cell research.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.hhs.gov/news/press/2004pres/20040714b.html |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20090109104735/http://www.hhs.gov/news/press/2004pres/20040714b.html |archivedate=2009-01-09 |publisher=US Department of Health and Human Services |title=Stem Cell FAQ |date=2004-07-14}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Amniotic==
Multipotent stem cells are also found in [[amniotic fluid]]. These stem cells are very active, expand extensively without feeders and are not tumorigenic. [[Amniotic stem cells]] are multipotent and can differentiate in cells of adipogenic, osteogenic, myogenic, endothelial, hepatic and also neuronal lines.&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite journal |vauthors=De Coppi P, Bartsch G, Siddiqui MM, Xu T, Santos CC, Perin L, Mostoslavsky G, Serre AC, Snyder EY, Yoo JJ, Furth ME, Soker S, Atala A | title = Isolation of amniotic stem cell lines with potential for therapy | journal = Nature Biotechnology | volume = 25 | issue = 5 | pages = 100–106 | year = 2007 | pmid = 17206138 | doi = 10.1038/nbt1274 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
Amniotic stem cells are a topic of active research.

Use of stem cells from [[amniotic fluid]] overcomes the ethical objections to using human embryos as a source of cells.  [[Roman Catholic]] teaching forbids the use of embryonic stem cells in experimentation; accordingly, the [[Holy See|Vatican]] newspaper "[[Osservatore Romano]]" called amniotic stem cells "the future of medicine".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.catholicnewsagency.com/news/vatican_newspaper_calls_new_stem_cell_source_future_of_medicine/ |title=Vatican newspaper calls new stem cell source 'future of medicine' :: Catholic News Agency (CNA) |publisher=Catholic News Agency |date=2010-02-03 |accessdate=2010-03-14}}&lt;/ref&gt;

It is possible to collect amniotic stem cells for donors or for autologuous use: the first US amniotic stem cells bank &lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.reuters.com/article/pressRelease/idUS166682+22-Oct-2009+PRN20091022 |title=European Biotech Company Biocell Center Opens First U.S. Facility for Preservation of Amniotic Stem Cells in Medford, Massachusetts |publisher=Reuters |date=2009-10-22 |accessdate=2010-03-14}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.boston.com/business/ticker/2009/10/europes_biocell.html |title=Europe's Biocell Center opens Medford office – Daily Business Update |work=The Boston Globe |date=2009-10-22 |accessdate=2010-03-14}}&lt;/ref&gt; was opened in 2009 in Medford, MA, by [[Biocell Center]] Corporation&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bostonherald.com/business/general/view/20091022the_ticker/ |title=The Ticker |publisher=BostonHerald.com |date=2009-10-22 |accessdate=2010-03-14}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url= http://www.masshightech.com/stories/2009/10/19/daily59-Biocell-Center-opens-amniotic-stem-cell-bank-in-Medford.html |title=Biocell Center opens amniotic stem cell bank in Medford |work=Mass High Tech Business News|date=2009-10-23 |accessdate=2012-08-26}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.wbur.org/2009/10/22/stem-cell-bank |title=News » World’s First Amniotic Stem Cell Bank Opens In Medford |publisher=wbur.org |accessdate=2010-03-14}}&lt;/ref&gt; and collaborates with various hospitals and universities all over the world.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.prnewswire.com/news-releases/biocell-center-corporation-partners-with-new-englands-largest-community-based-hospital-network-to-offer-a-unique-service-in-amniotic-fluid-stem-cell-preservation-86848157.html |title=Biocell Center Corporation Partners with New England's Largest Community-Based Hospital Network to Offer a Unique... – MEDFORD, Mass., March 8 /PRNewswire/ |location=Massachusetts |publisher=Prnewswire.com |accessdate=2010-03-14}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Induced pluripotent==
{{Main article|Induced pluripotent stem cell}}

Adult stem cells have limitations with their potency; unlike ESCs, they are not able to differentiate into cells from all three [[germ layers]]. As such, they are deemed [[cell potency|multipotent]].

However, [[reprogramming]] allows for the creation of pluripotent cells, [[induced pluripotent stem cell]]s, from adult cells. It is important to note that these are not adult stem cells, but adult cells (e.g. epithelial cells) reprogrammed to give rise to cells with pluripotent capabilities. Using genetic reprogramming with protein [[transcription factors]], pluripotent stem cells with [[embryonic Stem Cell|ESC]]-like capabilities have been derived.&lt;ref name="Economist2007_11_22"&gt;{{cite news|title=Making human embryonic stem cells|publisher=The Economist|url=http://www.economist.com/science/displaystory.cfm?story_id=10170972|date=2007-11-22}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.npr.org/templates/story/story.php?storyId=16466265|publisher=[[National Public Radio]]|title=Skin Cells Can Become Embryonic Stem Cells|author1=Brand, Madeleine |author2=Palca, Joe |author3=Cohen, Alex |date=2007-11-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.pbs.org/newshour/bb/science/july-dec07/stemcells_11-20.html|title=Breakthrough Set to Radically Change Stem Cell Debate|publisher=[[News Hour with Jim Lehrer]]|date=2007-11-20}}&lt;/ref&gt; The first demonstration of [[Induced Pluripotent Stem Cell]]s was conducted by [[Shinya Yamanaka]] and his colleagues at [[Kyoto University]].&lt;ref name = "overview"&gt;{{cite journal|pmid= 27908220|year= 2016|author1= Kimbrel|first1= E. A.|title= Pluripotent stem cells: The last 10 years|journal= Regenerative Medicine|volume= 11|issue= 8|pages= 831–847|last2= Lanza|first2= R|doi= 10.2217/rme-2016-0117}}&lt;/ref&gt; They used the [[transcription factors]] [[Oct-4|Oct3/4]], [[Sox2]], [[c-Myc]], and [[Klf4]] to reprogram mouse fibroblast cells into pluripotent cells.&lt;ref name="Economist2007_11_22"/&gt;&lt;ref name= "og Yak"&gt;{{cite journal|pmid= 16904174|year= 2006|author1= Takahashi|first1= K|title= Induction of pluripotent stem cells from mouse embryonic and adult fibroblast cultures by defined factors|journal= Cell|volume= 126|issue= 4|pages= 663–76|last2= Yamanaka|first2= S|doi= 10.1016/j.cell.2006.07.024}}&lt;/ref&gt; Subsequent work used these factors to induce pluripotency in human fibroblast cells.&lt;ref name= "2007 Yak"&gt;{{ cite journal|pmid= 18035408|year= 2007|author1= Takahashi|first1= K|title= Induction of pluripotent stem cells from adult human fibroblasts by defined factors|journal= Cell|volume= 131|issue= 5|pages= 861–72|last2= Tanabe|first2= K|last3= Ohnuki|first3= M|last4= Narita|first4= M|last5= Ichisaka|first5= T|last6= Tomoda|first6= K|last7= Yamanaka|first7= S|doi= 10.1016/j.cell.2007.11.019}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Junying Yu]], [[James Thomson (cell biologist)|James Thomson]], and their colleagues at the [[University of Wisconsin–Madison]] used a different set of factors, Oct4, Sox2, Nanog and Lin28, and carried out their experiments using cells from human [[foreskin]].&lt;ref name="Economist2007_11_22"/&gt;&lt;ref name = "wisconsin"&gt;{{cite journal|pmid= 18029452|year= 2007|author1= Yu|first1= J|title= Induced pluripotent stem cell lines derived from human somatic cells|journal= Science|volume= 318|issue= 5858|pages= 1917–20|last2= Vodyanik|first2= M. A.|last3= Smuga-Otto|first3= K|last4= Antosiewicz-Bourget|first4= J|last5= Frane|first5= J. L.|last6= Tian|first6= S|last7= Nie|first7= J|last8= Jonsdottir|first8= G. A.|last9= Ruotti|first9= V|last10= Stewart|first10= R|last11= Slukvin|first11= I. I.|last12= Thomson|first12= J. A.|doi= 10.1126/science.1151526}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, they were able to replicate [[Yamanaka]]'s finding that inducing pluripotency in human cells was possible.

It is important to note that iPSCs and ESCs are not equivalent. They have many similar properties, such as [[pluripotency]] and differentiation potential, the expression of [[pluripotency]] genes, [[epigenetic]] patterns, [[embryoid body]] and [[teratoma]] formation, and viable [[chimera (genetics)|chimera]] formation.&lt;ref name="overview" /&gt;&lt;ref name = "og Yak" /&gt; However, similar does not mean they are the same. In fact, there are many differences within these properties. Importantly, the chromatin of iPSCs appears to be more "closed" or methylated than that of ESCs.&lt;ref name="overview" /&gt;&lt;ref name = "og Yak" /&gt; Similarly, the gene expression pattern between ESCs and iPSCs, or even iPSCs sourced from different origins.&lt;ref name="overview" /&gt; There are thus questions about the "completeness" of [[reprogramming]] and the somatic memory of induced pluripotent stem cells. Despite this, inducing [[adult cell]]s to be pluripotent appears to be viable.

As a result of the success of these experiments, [[Ian Wilmut]], who helped create the first cloned animal [[Dolly the Sheep]], has announced that he will abandon [[somatic cell nuclear transfer]] as an avenue of research.&lt;ref&gt;"His inspiration comes from the research by Prof [[Shinya Yamanaka]] at [[Kyoto University]], which suggests a way to create human embryo stem cells without the need for human eggs, which are in extremely short supply, and without the need to create and destroy human cloned embryos, which is bitterly opposed by the pro life movement."{{cite news|url=http://www.telegraph.co.uk/science/science-news/3314696/Dolly-creator-Prof-Ian-Wilmut-shuns-cloning.html|title=Dolly creator Prof Ian Wilmut shuns cloning|author=Highfield, Roger |date=2007-11-16|publisher=[[The Daily Telegraph|The Telegraph]] | location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Furthermore, induced pluripotent stem cells provide several therapeutic advantages. Like ESCs, they are [[pluripotent]]. They thus have great differentiation potential; theoretically, they could produce any cell within the human body (if [[reprogramming]] to pluripotency was "complete").&lt;ref name = "overview" /&gt; Moreover, unlike ESCs, they potentially could allow doctors to create a pluripotent stem cell line for each individual patient.&lt;ref name="R&amp;D"&gt;{{cite journal|pmid= 22258608|pmc= 3652331|year= 2012|author1= Robinton|first1= D. A.|title= The promise of induced pluripotent stem cells in research and therapy|journal= Nature|volume= 481|issue= 7381|pages= 295–305|last2= Daley|first2= G. Q.|doi= 10.1038/nature10761}}&lt;/ref&gt; In fact, frozen blood samples can be used as a source of induced pluripotent stem cells, opening a new avenue for obtaining the valued cells.&lt;ref&gt;[https://web.archive.org/web/20100703175036/http://www.newsdaily.com/stories/tre6604si-us-stemcells-frozen/ Frozen blood a source of stem cells, study finds]. newsdaily.com (2010-07-01)&lt;/ref&gt; Patient specific stem cells allow for the screening for side effects before drug treatment, as well as the reduced risk of transplantation rejection.&lt;ref name= "R&amp;D" /&gt; Despite their current limited use therapeutically, iPSCs hold create potential for future use in medical treatment and research.

==Lineage==
{{Main article|Stem cell line}}
To ensure self-renewal, stem cells undergo two types of cell division (see ''Stem cell division and differentiation'' diagram). Symmetric division gives rise to two identical daughter cells both endowed with stem cell properties. Asymmetric division, on the other hand, produces only one stem cell and a [[progenitor cell]] with limited self-renewal potential. Progenitors can go through several rounds of cell division before terminally [[cell differentiation|differentiating]] into a mature cell. It is possible that the molecular distinction between symmetric and asymmetric divisions lies in differential segregation of cell membrane proteins (such as [[receptor (biochemistry)|receptors]]) between the daughter cells.&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite journal |vauthors=Beckmann J, Scheitza S, Wernet P, Fischer JC, Giebel B | title = Asymmetric cell division within the human hematopoietic stem and progenitor cell compartment: identification of asymmetrically segregating proteins | journal = Blood | volume = 109 | issue = 12 | pages = 5494–501 | year = 2007 | pmid = 17332245 | doi = 10.1182/blood-2006-11-055921 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

An alternative theory is that stem cells remain undifferentiated due to environmental cues in their particular niche. Stem cells differentiate when they leave that niche or no longer receive those signals. Studies in ''Drosophila'' germarium have identified the signals [[decapentaplegic]] and adherens junctions that prevent germarium stem cells from differentiating.&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite journal |vauthors=Xie T, Spradling AC | title = decapentaplegic is essential for the maintenance and division of germline stem cells in the Drosophila ovary | journal = Cell | volume = 94 | issue = 2 | pages = 251–60 | year = 1998 | pmid = 9695953 | doi = 10.1016/S0092-8674(00)81424-5 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite journal |vauthors=Song X, Zhu CH, Doan C, Xie T | title = Germline stem cells anchored by adherens junctions in the Drosophila ovary niches | journal = Science | volume = 296 | issue = 5574 | pages = 1855–7 | year = 2002 | pmid = 12052957 | doi = 10.1126/science.1069871 | bibcode = 2002Sci...296.1855S }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Treatments==
{{Main article|Stem cell therapy}}

Stem cell therapy is the use of stem cells to treat or prevent a disease or condition.  [[Bone marrow transplant]] is a form of stem cell therapy that has been used for many years without controversy. No stem cell therapies other than bone marrow transplant are widely used.&lt;ref&gt;Ian Murnaghan for Explore Stem Cells. Updated: 16 December 2013  [http://www.explorestemcells.co.uk/WhyPerformStemCellTransplant.html Why Perform a Stem Cell Transplant?]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=NCI&gt;[http://www.cancer.gov/cancertopics/factsheet/Therapy/bone-marrow-transplant Bone Marrow Transplantation and Peripheral Blood Stem Cell Transplantation] In National Cancer Institute Fact Sheet web site. Bethesda, MD: National Institutes of Health, U.S. Department of Health and Human Services, 2010.  Cited August 24, 2010&lt;/ref&gt;

===Disadvantages===
Stem cell treatments may require [[immunosuppression]] because of a requirement for radiation before the transplant to remove the person's previous cells, or because the patient's immune system may target the stem cells. One approach to avoid the second possibility is to use stem cells from the same patient who is being treated.

Pluripotency in certain stem cells could also make it difficult to obtain a specific cell type. It is also difficult to obtain the exact cell type needed, because not all cells in a population differentiate uniformly. Undifferentiated cells can create tissues other than desired types.&lt;ref&gt;Moore, Keith L., T.V.N. Persaud, and Mark G. Torchia. Before We Are Born: Essentials of Embryology and Birth Defects. Philadelphia, PA: Saunders, Elsevier. 2013 Print.&lt;/ref&gt;

Some stem cells form tumors after transplantation;&lt;ref name = "usn2009"&gt;Bernadine Healy, M.D.. [http://health.usnews.com/health-news/blogs/heart-to-heart/2009/03/04/why-embryonic-stem-cells-are-obsolete "Why Embryonic Stem Cells are obsolete"] ''US News and world report''. Retrieved on Aug 17, 2015.&lt;/ref&gt; pluripotency is linked to tumor formation especially in embryonic stem cells, fetal proper stem cells, induced pluripotent stem cells. Fetal proper stem cells form tumors despite multipotency.{{Citation needed|date=November 2013}}

==Research==
{{Further information|Consumer Watchdog vs. Wisconsin Alumni Research Foundation}}

Some of the fundamental [[patent]]s covering human embryonic stem cells are owned by the [[Wisconsin Alumni Research Foundation]] (WARF) – they are patents 5,843,780, 6,200,806, and 7,029,913 invented by [[James Thomson (cell biologist)|James A. Thomson]]. WARF does not enforce these patents against academic scientists, but does enforce them against companies.&lt;ref name = "stemcellPatent"&gt;Regalado, Antonio, David P. Hamilton (July 2006). [http://www.geneticsandsociety.org/article.php?id=1896 "How a University's Patents May Limit Stem-Cell Researcher."] ''The Wall Street Journal''. Retrieved on July 24, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2006, a request for the [[US Patent and Trademark Office]] (USPTO) to re-examine the three patents was filed by the [[Public Patent Foundation]] on behalf of its client, the non-profit patent-watchdog group [[Consumer Watchdog]] (formerly the Foundation for Taxpayer and Consumer Rights).&lt;ref name = "stemcellPatent"/&gt;   In the re-examination process, which involves several rounds of discussion between the USTPO and the parties, the USPTO initially agreed with Consumer Watchdog and rejected all the claims in all three patents,&lt;ref&gt;Stephen Jenei for Patent Baristas, April 3, 2007 [http://www.patentbaristas.com/archives/2007/04/03/warf-stem-cell-patents-knocked-down-in-round-one/ WARF Stem Cell Patents Knocked Down in Round One]&lt;/ref&gt; however in response, WARF amended the claims of all three patents to make them more narrow, and in 2008 the USPTO found the amended claims in all three patents to be patentable. The decision on one of the patents (7,029,913) was appealable, while the decisions on the other two were not.&lt;ref&gt;Stephen Jenei for Patent Baristas, March 3, 2008 [http://www.patentbaristas.com/archives/2008/03/03/ding-warf-wins-round-2-as-stem-cell-patent-upheld/ Ding! WARF Wins Round 2 As Stem Cell Patent Upheld]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Constance Holden for Science Now. March 12, 2008 [http://news.sciencemag.org/2008/03/warf-goes-3-3-patents WARF Goes 3 for 3 on Patents]&lt;/ref&gt; Consumer Watchdog appealed the granting of the '913 patent to the USTPO's Board of Patent Appeals and Interferences (BPAI) which granted the appeal, and in 2010 the BPAI decided that the amended claims of the '913 patent were not patentable.&lt;ref&gt;Stephen G. Kunin for Patents Post Grant. May 10, 2010 [http://www.patentspostgrant.com/lang/en/2010/05/bpai-rejects-warf-stem-cell-patent-claims-in-inter-partes-reexamination-appeal BPAI Rejects WARF Stem Cell Patent Claims in Inter Partes Reexamination Appeal]&lt;/ref&gt;  However, WARF was able to re-open prosecution of the case and did so, amending the claims of the '913 patent again to make them more narrow, and in January 2013 the amended claims were allowed.&lt;ref&gt;United States Patent And Trademark Office. Board Of Patent Appeals and Interferences. The Foundation For Taxpayer &amp; Consumer Rights, Requester And Appellant  V. Patent Of Wisconsin Alumni Research Foundation, Patent Owner And Respondent.  Appeal 2012-011693, Reexamination Control 95/000,154. Patent 7,029,913 [http://e-foia.uspto.gov/Foia/ReterivePdf?system=BPAI&amp;flNm=fd2012011693-01-22-2013-1 Decision on Appeal]&lt;/ref&gt;

In July 2013, Consumer Watchdog announced that it would appeal the decision to allow the claims of the '913 patent to the US [[Court of Appeals for the Federal Circuit]] (CAFC), the federal appeals court that hears patent cases.&lt;ref&gt;GenomeWeb staff, July 03, 2013 [http://www.genomeweb.com/consumer-watchdog-ppf-seek-invalidation-warfs-stem-cell-patent Consumer Watchdog, PPF Seek Invalidation of WARF's Stem Cell Patent]&lt;/ref&gt;  At a hearing in December 2013, the CAFC raised the question of whether Consumer Watchdog had [[legal standing]] to appeal; the case could not proceed until that issue was resolved.&lt;ref&gt;Antoinette Konski for Personalized Medicine Bulletin. February 3, 2014 [http://www.personalizedmedicinebulletin.com/2014/02/03/u-s-government-and-uspto-urges-federal-circuit-to-dismiss-stem-cell-appeal/ U.S. Government and USPTO Urges Federal Circuit to Dismiss Stem Cell Appeal]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Treatment===
[[File:Stem cell treatments.svg|thumb|330px|Diseases and conditions where stem cell treatment is being investigated.]]
Diseases and conditions where stem cell treatment is being investigated include:
* [[Diabetes]]&lt;ref name="nih" /&gt;
* [[Rheumatoid arthritis]]&lt;ref name="nih" /&gt;
* [[Parkinson's disease]]&lt;ref name="nih" /&gt;
* [[Alzheimer's disease]]&lt;ref name="nih" /&gt;
* [[Osteoarthritis]]&lt;ref name="nih"&gt;[http://stemcells.nih.gov/info/basics/pages/basics6.aspx Stem Cell Basics: What are the potential uses of human stem cells and the obstacles that must be overcome before these potential uses will be realized?]. In Stem Cell Information World Wide Web site. Bethesda, MD: National Institutes of Health, U.S. Department of Health and Human Services, 2009. cited Sunday, April 26, 2009&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Stroke]] and [[traumatic brain injury]] repair&lt;ref&gt;Steinberg, Douglas (November 2000) [http://www.mult-sclerosis.org/news/Dec2000/StemCellDebatePartII.html Stem Cells Tapped to Replenish Organs] thescientist.com&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Learning disability]] due to [[congenital disorder]] &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.israel21c.org/health/israeli-scientists-reverse-brain-birth-defects-using-stem-cells ISRAEL21c: Israeli scientists reverse brain birth defects using stem cells] December 25, 2008. (Researchers from the Hebrew University of Jerusalem-Hadassah Medical led by Prof. Joseph Yanai)&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Spinal cord injury]] repair &lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |vauthors=Kang KS, Kim SW, Oh YH, Yu JW, Kim KY, Park HK, Song CH, Han H | title = A 37-year-old spinal cord-injured female patient, transplanted of multipotent stem cells from human UC blood, with improved sensory perception and mobility, both functionally and morphologically: a case study | journal = Cytotherapy | volume = 7 | issue = 4 | pages = 368–73 | year = 2005 | pmid = 16162459 | doi = 10.1080/14653240500238160 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Heart infarction]] &lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |vauthors=Strauer BE, Schannwell CM, Brehm M | title = Therapeutic potentials of stem cells in cardiac diseases | journal = Minerva Cardioangiol | volume = 57 | issue = 2 | pages = 249–67 | year = 2009 | pmid = 19274033 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Anti-[[cancer]] treatments &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.mult-sclerosis.org/news/Dec2000/StemCellDebatePartII.html Stem Cells Tapped to Replenish Organs] thescientist.com, Nov 2000. By Douglas Steinberg&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Baldness]] reversal&lt;ref&gt;[https://web.archive.org/web/20080530042215rn_3/www.webmd.com/skin-problems-and-treatments/hair-loss/news/20041104/hair-cloning-nears-reality-as-baldness-cure ''Hair Cloning Nears Reality as Baldness Cure''] [[WebMD]] November 2004&lt;/ref&gt;
* Replace missing [[teeth]] &lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |vauthors=Yen AH, Sharpe PT | title = Stem cells and tooth tissue engineering | journal = Cell Tissue Res. | volume = 331 | issue = 1 | pages = 359–72 | year = 2008 | pmid = 17938970 | doi = 10.1007/s00441-007-0467-6 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Repair [[hearing]] &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.newscientist.com/article/dn7003|title=Gene therapy is first deafness 'cure'|publisher=New Scientist|date=February 14, 2005}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Restore [[Visual system|vision]] &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/england/southern_counties/4495419.stm|title= Stem cells used to restore vision|publisher=BBC News}}&lt;/ref&gt; and repair damage to the [[cornea]]&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|title = Transplantation of human embryonic stem cells onto a partially wounded human cornea in vitro|journal = Acta Ophthalmologica|date = 2013-03-01|issn = 1755-3768|pmc = 3660785|pmid = 22280565|pages = 127–130|volume = 91|issue = 2|doi = 10.1111/j.1755-3768.2011.02358.x|first = Charles|last = Hanson|first2 = Thorir|last2 = Hardarson|first3 = Catharina|last3 = Ellerström|first4 = Markus|last4 = Nordberg|first5 = Gunilla|last5 = Caisander|first6 = Mahendra|last6 = Rao|first7 = Johan|last7 = Hyllner|first8 = Ulf|last8 = Stenevi}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Amyotrophic lateral sclerosis]] &lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | author = Vastag B | title = Stem Cells Step Closer to the Clinic: Paralysis Partially Reversed in Rats with ALS-like Disease | journal = JAMA: The Journal of the American Medical Association | volume = 285 | issue = 13 | pages = 1691–1693 | year = 2001 | pmid = 11277806 | pmc =  | doi = 10.1001/jama.285.13.1691 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Crohn's disease]] &lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |author = Anderson, Querida|title = Osiris Trumpets Its Adult Stem Cell Product|url = http://www.genengnews.com/articles/chitem.aspx?aid=2508|work = [[Gen. Eng. Biotechnol. News|Genetic Engineering &amp; Biotechnology News]]|publisher = [[Mary Ann Liebert, Inc.]]|page = 13|date = 2008-06-15|accessdate = 2008-07-06|quote = (subtitle) Procymal is being developed in many indications, GvHD being the most advanced}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Wound healing]] &lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |vauthors=Gurtner GC, Callaghan MJ, Longaker MT | title = Progress and potential for regenerative medicine | journal = Annu. Rev. Med. | volume = 58 | issue =  | pages = 299–312 | year = 2007 | pmid = 17076602 | doi = 10.1146/annurev.med.58.082405.095329 }} Bone marrow transplantation is, as of 2009, the only established use of stem cells.&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Male infertility]] due to absence of spermatogonial stem cells &lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |vauthors=Hanna V, Gassei K, Orwig KE | title = Stem Cell Therapies for Male Infertility: Where Are We Now and Where Are We Going? | journal = Biennial Review of Infertility | year = 2015 }} Bone marrow transplantation is, as of 2009, the only established use of stem cells.&lt;/ref&gt;

Research is underway to develop various sources for stem cells, and to apply stem cell treatments for [[neurodegenerative diseases]] and conditions, [[diabetes]], [[heart disease]], and other conditions.&lt;ref name="pmid23131007"&gt;{{cite journal |vauthors=Bubela T, Li MD, Hafez M, Bieber M, Atkins H | title = Is belief larger than fact: Expectations, optimism and reality for translational stem cell research | journal = BMC Med | volume = 10 | issue =  | pages = 133 | year = 2012 | pmid = 23131007 | pmc = 3520764 | doi = 10.1186/1741-7015-10-133 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Research is also underway in generating [[organoid]]s using stem cells, which would allow for further understanding of human development, [[organogenesis]], and modeling of human diseases.&lt;ref&gt;Ader, M., &amp; Tanaka, E. M. (2014). Modeling human development in 3D culture. Current Opinion in Cell Biology, 31, 23-28. {{doi|10.1016/j.ceb.2014.06.013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In more recent years, with the ability of scientists to isolate and culture [[embryonic stem cells]], and with scientists' growing ability to create stem cells using [[somatic cell nuclear transfer]] and techniques to create [[induced pluripotent stem cells]], controversy has crept in, both related to [[abortion debate|abortion politics]] and to [[human cloning]].

[[Hepatotoxicity]] and drug-induced liver injury account for a substantial number of failures of new drugs in development and market withdrawal, highlighting the need for screening assays such as stem cell-derived hepatocyte-like cells, that are capable of detecting toxicity early in the [[drug development]] process.&lt;ref name="stem2012"&gt;{{cite journal |vauthors=Greenhough S, Hay DC |title=Stem Cell-Based Toxicity Screening: Recent Advances in Hepatocyte Generation |url=http://adisonline.com/pharmaceuticalmedicine/Abstract/2012/26020/Stem_Cell_Based_Toxicity_Screening__Recent.2.aspx |journal=Pharm Med |volume=26 |issue=2 |pages=85–89 |year=2012 |doi= 10.1007/BF03256896}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
*[[Cell bank]]
*[[Human genome]]
*[[Meristem]]
*[[Partial cloning]]
*[[Plant stem cell]]
*[[Stem cell controversy]]
*[[Stem cell marker]]
*[[Shinya Yamanaka]]

==References==
{{Reflist|35em}}

==External links==
{{Commons category|Stem cells}}
&lt;!-- Please use the talk page to propose any additions to this section.  If you do not do this, the link will almost certainly be deleted.--&gt;
;General
{{Library resources box |by=no |onlinebooks=no |others=yes lcheading=Stem cells}}
*[http://stemcells.nih.gov/info/basics/ Stem Cell Basics] Courtesy of the National Institutes of Health
*[http://www.nature.com/stemcells Nature Reports Stem Cells: Introductory material, research advances and debates concerning stem cell research.]
*[http://dels.nas.edu/bls/stemcells/booklet.shtml Understanding Stem Cells: A View of the Science and Issues from the National Academies]
*[http://www.scientificamerican.com/article.cfm?id=the-stem-cell-challenge Scientific American Magazine (June 2004 Issue) The Stem Cell Challenge]
*[http://www.scientificamerican.com/article.cfm?id=stem-cells-the-real-culpr-2006-07 Scientific American Magazine (July 2006 Issue) Stem Cells: The Real Culprits in Cancer?]
*{{cite SEP |url-id=stem-cells |title=Ethics of Stem Cell Research |last=Siegel |first=Andrew}}
*[http://www.hopkinsmedicine.org/stem_cell_research Stem Cell Research at Johns Hopkins]
*[http://www.stembook.org/ StemBook]

{{Wound healing}}
{{Stem cells}}
{{Breakthrough of the Year}}

{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Stem Cell}}
[[Category:Stem cells| ]]
[[Category:Induced stem cells]]
[[Category:Biotechnology]]
[[Category:Cell biology]]
[[Category:Cloning]]
[[Category:Developmental biology]]</text>
      <sha1>60v7roio0tk5wwvoqmrpk9gj1vuzs0u</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>