<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<mediawiki xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <page>
    <title>Biomimetics</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>45784</id>
    <revision>
      <id>792617104</id>
      <parentid>792616860</parentid>
      <timestamp>2017-07-27T15:49:31Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Ronz</username>
        <id>7862</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>restore intro</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">'''Biomimetics''' or '''biomimicry''' is the imitation of the models, systems, and elements of nature for the purpose of solving complex [[human]] problems.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last1=Vincent|first1=Julian F. V.|title=Biomimetics: its practice and theory|url=http://rsif.royalsocietypublishing.org/content/3/9/471|accessdate=7 April 2015|doi=10.1098/rsif.2006.0127|date=22 August 2006|display-authors=etal}}&lt;/ref&gt; The terms "biomimetics" and "biomimicry" derive from {{lang-grc|βίος}} (''bios''), life, and μίμησις (''[[mimesis|mīmēsis]]''), imitation, from μιμεῖσθαι (''mīmeisthai''), to imitate, from μῖμος (''mimos''), actor. A closely related field is '''[[bionics]]'''.&lt;ref name=McCarty/&gt;
{{multiple image
 | total_width       = 410
 | caption_align     = center
 | image1            = Bur Macro BlackBg.jpg
 | width1            = 2184
 | height1           = 1760
 | alt1              = burr
 | caption1          = The tiny hooks on [[bur]] fruits ...
 | image2            = Klettverschluss.jpg
 | width2            = 1600
 | height2           = 1022
 | alt2              = velcro tape
 | caption2          = ... inspired [[Velcro]] tape.
}}
Living organisms have [[evolution|evolved]] [[adaptation (biology)|well-adapted]] structures and materials over geological time through [[natural selection]]. Biomimetics has given rise to new technologies inspired by [[biological]] solutions at macro and nanoscales. Humans have looked at nature for answers to problems throughout our existence. Nature has solved engineering problems such as self-healing abilities, environmental exposure tolerance and resistance, [[hydrophobicity]], self-assembly, and harnessing solar energy.

== History ==

One of the early examples of would-be biomimicry was the study of birds to enable human flight. Although never successful in creating a "flying machine", [[Leonardo da Vinci]] (1452–1519) was a keen observer of the anatomy and flight of birds, and made numerous notes and sketches on his observations as well as sketches of "flying machines".&lt;ref name="Romei 2008 56"/&gt; The [[Wright Brothers]], who succeeded in flying the first heavier-than-air aircraft in 1903, allegedly derived inspiration from observations of pigeons in flight.&lt;ref&gt;Compare: {{Cite book | last=Howard | first=Fred | title=Wilbur and Orville: A Biography of the Wright Brothers | publisher=Dober Publications | year=1998 | location=| page=33 | isbn=978-0-486-40297-0 | quote = According to Wilbur, he and his brother discovered the birds' method of lateral control one day while observing a flight of pigeons. [...] 'Although we intently watched birds fly in a hope of learning something from them,' [Orville] wrote in 1941, 'I cannot think of anything that was first learned in that way.'}}&lt;/ref&gt;

During the 1950s the American [[biophysicist]] and [[polymath]] [[Otto Schmitt]] developed the concept of "biomimetics".&lt;ref name="Vincent2006"&gt;{{cite journal |last= Vincent |first= Julian F.V. |author2= Bogatyreva, Olga A. |author3= Bogatyrev, Nikolaj R. |author4= Bowyer, Adrian |author5= Pahl, Anja-Karina |title= Biomimetics: its practice and theory |journal= Journal of The Royal Society Interface |date= 21 August 2006|volume= 3|issue= 9|pages= 471–482|doi= 10.1098/rsif.2006.0127 |pmid= 16849244 |pmc= 1664643}}&lt;/ref&gt; During his doctoral research he developed the [[Schmitt trigger]] by studying the nerves in squid, attempting to engineer a device that replicated the biological system of [[nerve impulse|nerve propagation]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title= Otto H. Schmitt, Como People of the Past |url= https://sites.google.com/a/comogreenvillage.info/como-history/home/people-of-the-past-documents/como-people-of-the-past/otto-h-schmitt |publisher= Connie Sullivan, Como History Article}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{qn|date=June 2017}} He continued to focus on devices that mimic natural systems and by 1957 he had perceived a converse to the standard view of biophysics at that time, a view he would come to call biomimetics.&lt;ref name="Vincent2006"/&gt;

{{quote|Biophysics is not so much a subject matter as it is a point of view. It is an approach to problems of biological science utilizing the theory and technology of the physical sciences. Conversely, biophysics is also a biologist's approach to problems of physical science and engineering, although this aspect has largely been neglected.|Otto Herbert Schmitt|In Appreciation, A Lifetime of Connections: Otto Herbert Schmitt, 1913 - 1998}}

In 1960 [[Jack E. Steele]] coined a similar term, ''[[bionics]]'', at Wright-Patterson Air Force Base in Dayton, Ohio, where Otto Schmitt also worked. Steele defined bionics as "the science of systems which have some function copied from nature, or which represent characteristics of natural systems or their analogues".&lt;ref name=McCarty&gt;Mary McCarty. [https://web.archive.org/web/20110604025951/http://www.daytondailynews.com/o/content/oh/story/opinions/columns/2009/01/29/ddn012909mary.html?cxntlid=inform_sr "Life of bionics founder a fine adventure"]. ''Dayton Daily News'', 29 January 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="vincent-2009"&gt;{{cite journal |last= Vincent|first= Julian F. V. |title= Biomimetics -- a review |journal= Journal of Engineering in Medicine |date= November 2009|volume= 223 |series= Proceedings of the Institution of Mechanical Engineers. Part H |issue= 8 |pages= 919–939 |doi= 10.1243/09544119JEIM561}}&lt;/ref&gt; During a later meeting in 1963 Schmitt stated,

{{quote|Let us consider what bionics has come to mean operationally and what it or some word like it (I prefer biomimetics) ought to mean in order to make good use of the technical skills of scientists specializing, or rather, I should say, despecializing into this area of research|Otto Herbert Schmitt|In Appreciation, A Lifetime of Connections: Otto Herbert Schmitt, 1913 - 1998}}

In 1969 Schmitt used the term “biomimetic“ in the title one of his papers,&lt;ref&gt;Schmitt O. Third Int. Biophysics Congress. 1969. Some interesting and useful biomimetic transforms. p. 297.&lt;/ref&gt; and by 1974 it had found its way into [[Webster's Dictionary]], bionics entered the same dictionary earlier in 1960 as "a science concerned with the application of data about the functioning of biological systems to the solution of engineering problems". Bionic took on a different connotation when [[Martin Caidin]] referenced Jack Steele and his work in the novel ''Cyborg'' which later resulted in the 1974 television series ''[[The Six Million Dollar Man]]'' and its spin-offs. The term bionic then became associated with "the use of electronically operated artificial body parts" and "having ordinary human powers increased by or as if by the aid of such devices".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=Compact Oxford English Dictionary |year=2008 |publisher= |location= |isbn=978-0-19-953296-4}}&lt;/ref&gt; Because the term ''bionic'' took on the implication of supernatural strength, the scientific community in [[english language|English]] speaking countries largely abandoned it.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal | last =Vincent | first =JFV | title =Biomimetics — a review | journal =Proc. I. Mech. E.| volume =223 | issue=| pages=919–939 | publisher=| year=2009 | url=| issn=| doi =}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The term ''biomimicry'' appeared as early as 1982.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal | last=Merrill | first=Connie Lange | title=Biomimicry of the Dioxygen Active Site in the Copper Proteins Hemocyanin and Cytochrome Oxidase  | location=Rice University  | year=1982  | accessdate=}}&lt;/ref&gt; Biomimicry was popularized by scientist and author [[Janine Benyus]] in her 1997 book ''Biomimicry: Innovation Inspired by Nature''. Biomimicry is defined in the book as a "new science that studies nature's models and then imitates or takes inspiration from these designs and processes to solve human problems". Benyus suggests looking to Nature as a "Model, Measure, and Mentor" and emphasizes sustainability as an objective of biomimicry.&lt;ref name="Benyus 1997"&gt;{{cite book |last=Benyus |first=Janine |title=Biomimicry: Innovation Inspired by Nature |year=1997 |publisher=[[William Morrow &amp; Company]] |location=New York, USA |isbn=978-0-688-16099-9 |ref=Benyus97}}&lt;/ref&gt; In addition to the benefits of sustainability, using biomimicry to create innovative materials, systems and architecture also results in businesses being able to do more at a lower cost, increasing production and profits. &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Biomimicry|url=https://biologydictionary.net/biomimicry|website=biologydictionary.net|accessdate=3 July 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Commercial applications ==

=== Fabrication ===
[[File:TobaccoMosaicVirus.jpg|thumb|upright|alt=Electron micrograph of rod shaped TMV particles.|[[Scanning electron micrograph]] of rod shaped [[tobacco mosaic virus]] particles]]

[[Biomineralization|Biomorphic mineralization]] is a technique that produces materials with morphologies and structures resembling those of natural living organisms by using bio-structures as templates for mineralization.  Compared to other methods of material production, biomorphic mineralization is facile, environmentally benign and economic.&lt;ref name="Tong"&gt;Tong-Xiang, Suk-Kwun, Di Zhang. "Biomorphic Mineralization: From biology to materials." State Key Lab of Metal Matrix Composites. Shanghai: Shanghai Jiaotong University, n.d. 545-1000.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Display technology===
{{Further information|Structural coloration|Patterns in nature}}

 [[File:Morpho didius Male Dos MHNT.jpg|thumb|alt=Morpho butterfly.|Vibrant blue color of ''[[Morpho]]'' butterfly due to [[structural coloration]]]]

''[[Morpho]]'' butterfly wings contain microstructures that create its coloring effect through [[structural coloration]] rather than [[pigment]]ation.  Incident light waves are reflected at specific wavelengths to create vibrant colors due to multilayer interference, diffraction, thin film interference, and scattering properties.&lt;ref name=Ball&gt;{{cite news | url=http://www.nature.com/scientificamerican/journal/v306/n5/full/scientificamerican0512-74.html | title=Scientific American | work=Nature's Color Tricks | date=May 2012 | accessdate=3 June 2012 | author=Ball, Philip |volume=306 | pages=74–79 |doi=10.1038/scientificamerican0512-74}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The scales of these butterflies consist of microstructures such as ridges, cross-ribs, ridge-lamellae, and microribs that have been shown to be responsible for coloration. The structural color has been simply explained as the interference due to alternating layers of cuticle and air using a model of [[Thin-film interference|multilayer interference]]. The same principles behind the coloration of [[soap bubble]]s apply to butterfly wings. The color of butterfly wings is due to multiple instances of constructive [[Interference (wave propagation)|interference]] from structures such as this. The photonic microstructure of butterfly wings can be replicated through biomorphic mineralization to yield similar properties.  The photonic microstructures can be replicated using metal oxides or metal alkoxides such as titanium sulfate (TiSO&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt;), [[zirconium oxide]] (ZrO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;), and [[aluminium oxide]] (Al&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;).  An alternative method of vapor-phase oxidation of SiH4 on the template surface was found to preserve delicate structural features of the microstructure.&lt;ref&gt;Cook G., Timms P.L., Goltner-Spickermann C. Angew. "Chem Int Ed." 2003. 42:557.&lt;/ref&gt; A display technology ("Mirasol") based on the reflective properties of ''[[Morpho]]'' [[butterfly]] wings was commercialized by [[Qualcomm]] in 2007.  The technology uses [[Interferometric modulator display|Interferometric Modulation]] to reflect light so only the desired color is visible in each individual pixel of the display.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last1=Cathey|first1=Jim|title=Nature Knows Best: What Burrs, Geckos and Termites Teach Us About Design|url=https://www.qualcomm.com/blog/2010/01/07/nature-knows-best|publisher=Qualcomm|accessdate=24 August 2015|date=7 January 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;!--do not add anything here without a citation, or that is not in actual commercial use – it will be removed--&gt;

==Possible future applications==
[[File:Leonardo Design for a Flying Machine, c. 1488.jpg|thumb|200px|[[Leonardo da Vinci]]'s [[Science and inventions of Leonardo da Vinci#Flight|design for a flying machine]] with wings based closely upon the structure of bat wings]]

Biomimetics could in principle be applied in many fields. Because of the complexity of biological systems, the number of features that might be imitated is large. Biomimetic applications are at various stages of development from technologies that might become commercially usable to prototypes.&lt;ref&gt;Bharat Bhushan (15 March 2009) Biomimetics: lessons from nature–an overview http://rsta.royalsocietypublishing.org/content/367/1893/1445.full&lt;/ref&gt;

===Prototypes===

Researchers studied the termite's ability to maintain virtually constant temperature and humidity in their termite mounds in Africa despite outside temperatures that vary from 1.5&amp;nbsp;°C to 40&amp;nbsp;°C (35&amp;nbsp;°F to 104&amp;nbsp;°F).  Researchers initially scanned a termite mound and created 3-D images of the mound structure, which revealed construction that could influence human building design. The [[Eastgate Centre, Harare|Eastgate Centre]], a mid-rise office complex in [[Harare]], [[Zimbabwe]],&lt;ref name=BI&gt;[http://biomimicry.org/biomimicry-examples#architecture Biomimicry Examples — Biomimicry Institute]&lt;/ref&gt; stays cool without air conditioning and uses only 10% of the energy of a conventional building of the same size.

In structural engineering, the Swiss Federal Institute of Technology ([[EPFL]]) has incorporated biomimetic characteristics in an adaptive deployable "tensegrity" bridge. The bridge can carry out self-diagnosis and self-repair.&lt;ref name="korkmaz"&gt;{{cite journal | last=Korkmaz|first=Sinan |author2=Bel Hadj Ali, Nizar |author3=Smith, Ian F.C. | title=Determining Control Strategies for Damage Tolerance of an Active Tensegrity Structure | journal= Engineering Structures | doi=10.1016/j.engstruct.2011.02.031 | volume=33 | pages=1930–1939 | year=2011 | url =http://infoscience.epfl.ch/record/164609/files/Korkmaz%20et%20al,%20Determining%20Control%20Strategies%20for%20Damage%20Tolerance%20of%20an%20Active%20Tensegrity%20Structure,%20Engineering%20Structures%20(2011)_2.pdf | issue=6 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;!--do not add anything here without a citation – it will be removed--&gt;

===Technologies===

Practical underwater adhesion is an engineering challenge since current technology is unable to stick surface strongly underwater because of barriers such as hydration layers and contaminants on surfaces. However, marine [[mussel]]s can stick easily and efficiently to surfaces underwater under the harsh conditions of the ocean. They use strong filaments to adhere to rocks in the inter-tidal zones of wave-swept beaches, preventing them from being swept away in strong sea currents. Mussel foot proteins attach the filaments to rocks, boats and practically any surface in nature including other mussels. These proteins contain a mix of [[amino acid]] residues which has been adapted specifically for [[adhesive]] purposes. Researchers from the University of California Santa Barbara borrowed and simplified chemistries that the mussel foot uses to overcome this engineering challenge of wet adhesion to create copolyampholytes,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|title = Microphase Behavior and Enhanced Wet-Cohesion of Synthetic Copolyampholytes Inspired by a Mussel Foot Protein|url = http://dx.doi.org/10.1021/jacs.5b03827|journal = Journal of the American Chemical Society|date = 2015-07-29|issn = 0002-7863|pages = 9214–9217|volume = 137|issue = 29|doi = 10.1021/jacs.5b03827|first = Sungbaek|last = Seo|first2 = Saurabh|last2 = Das|first3 = Piotr J.|last3 = Zalicki|first4 = Razieh|last4 = Mirshafian|first5 = Claus D.|last5 = Eisenbach|first6 = Jacob N.|last6 = Israelachvili|first7 = J. Herbert|last7 = Waite|first8 = B. Kollbe|last8 = Ahn|pmid=26172268}}&lt;/ref&gt; and one-component adhesive systems&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|title = High-performance mussel-inspired adhesives of reduced complexity|url = http://www.nature.com/ncomms/2015/151019/ncomms9663/full/ncomms9663.html|journal = Nature Communications|date = 2015-10-19|volume = 6|doi = 10.1038/ncomms9663|language = en|first = B. Kollbe|last = Ahn|first2 = Saurabh|last2 = Das|first3 = Roscoe|last3 = Linstadt|first4 = Yair|last4 = Kaufman|first5 = Nadine R.|last5 = Martinez-Rodriguez|first6 = Razieh|last6 = Mirshafian|first7 = Ellina|last7 = Kesselman|first8 = Yeshayahu|last8 = Talmon|first9 = Bruce H.|last9 = Lipshutz|pages=8663|pmid=26478273|pmc=4667698}}&lt;/ref&gt; with potential for employment in [[nanofabrication]] protocols.

[[Spider]] web silk is as strong as the [[Kevlar]] used in [[Ballistic vest|bulletproof vests]]. Engineers could in principle use such a material, if it could be reengineered to have a long enough life, for parachute lines, suspension bridge cables, artificial ligaments for medicine, and other purposes.&lt;ref name="Benyus 1997"/&gt; Other research has proposed adhesive glue from [[mussel]]s, solar cells made like leaves, fabric that emulates [[shark]] skin, harvesting water from fog like a [[beetle]], and more.&lt;ref name=BI/&gt; [[Murray's law]], which in conventional form determined the optimum diameter of blood vessels, has been re-derived to provide simple equations for the pipe or tube diameter which gives a minimum mass engineering system.&lt;ref name="williams"&gt;{{cite journal | last=Williams|first=Hugo R. |author2=Trask, Richard S. |author3=Weaver, Paul M. |author4=Bond, Ian P. | title=Minimum mass vascular networks in multifunctional materials | journal=Journal of the Royal Society Interface | doi=10.1098/rsif.2007.1022 | volume=5 | pages=55–65 | year=2008 | url=http://rsif.royalsocietypublishing.org/content/5/18/55.full | pmid=17426011 | issue=18 | pmc=2605499}}&lt;/ref&gt; Aircraft wing design &lt;ref name="Romei 2008 56"&gt;{{Cite book | last=Romei | first=Francesca | title=Leonardo Da Vinci | publisher=The Oliver Press  | year=2008 | location=| page=56 | isbn=978-1-934545-00-3}}&lt;/ref&gt; and flight techniques&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.newscientist.com/article/dn24951-drone-with-legs-can-perch-watch-and-walk-like-a-bird.html#.U0lxhuZdWcI |title=Drone with legs can perch, watch and walk like a bird |work=Tech |publisher=New Scientist |date=27 January 2014 |accessdate=17 July 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; are being inspired by birds and bats.

Robots based on the physiology and methods of locomotion of animals include [[BionicKangaroo]] which moves like a kangaroo, saving energy from one jump and transferring it to its next jump,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://spectrum.ieee.org/automaton/robotics/robotics-hardware/festo-newest-robot-is-a-hopping-bionic-kangaroo |title=''Festo's Newest Robot Is a Hopping Bionic Kangaroo'' |last1=Ackerman |first1=Evan |date=2 Apr 2014 |website=spectrum.ieee.org |publisher=[[IEEE Spectrum]] |access-date=17 Apr 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; and climbing robots,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.newscientisttech.com/channel/tech/mg19025526.500.html Gecko-like robot scampers up the wall – tech – 23 May 2006 – New Scientist Tech]&lt;/ref&gt; boots and tape&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.stanford.edu/group/mota/education/Physics%2087N%20Final%20Projects/Group%20Gamma/gecko.htm |title=Gecko Tape |publisher=[[Stanford University]] |accessdate=17 July 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Synthetic setae|mimicking geckos feet and their ability for adhesive reversal]]. [[Dash Robotics, Inc|Kamigami Robots,]] a children's toy, mimic cockroach locomotion to run quickly and efficiently over indoor and outdoor surfaces.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://cra.org/robotics-highlight-kamigami-cockroach-inspired-robotics/|title=Robotics Highlight: Kamigami Cockroach Inspired Robotics|date=2016-07-18|work=CRA|access-date=2017-05-16|language=en-US}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Sharklet (material)|Nanotechnology surfaces]] that recreate properties of [[Dermal denticle#Placoid scales|shark skin]] are intended to enable more efficient movement through water.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://sharklet.com/technology/ | title='Inspired by Nature' | publisher=Sharklet Technologies Inc | date=2010 | accessdate=6 June 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Tire treads have been inspired by the toe pads of [[tree frog]]s.&lt;ref&gt;[http://iopscience.iop.org/0953-8984/19/37/376110 Tire treads inspired by tree frogs]&lt;/ref&gt; The self-sharpening teeth of many animals have been copied to make better cutting tools.&lt;ref&gt;[http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1002/adfm.201001546/abstract;jsessionid=E2E9980D17B063A5D9F5B2CFE4EDD85D.d02t01 Wiley: self-sharpening teeth]&lt;/ref&gt; [[Protein folding]] is used to control material formation for [[Molecular self-assembly|self-assembled functional nanostructures]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.jnanobiotechnology.com/content/12/1/4 Self-assembled nanostructures]&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Structural coloration]] of butterfly wings is adapted to provide improved [[interferometric modulator display]]s and everlasting colours.&lt;ref&gt;[http://iopscience.iop.org/1468-6996/12/6/064709 IOP Science: structurally colored displays]&lt;/ref&gt; New ceramics copy the properties of seashells.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Yao | first1 = Y. | last2 = Wang | first2 = Q. | last3 = Wang | first3 = H. | last4 = Zhang | first4 = B. | last5 = Zhao | first5 = C. | last6 = Wang | first6 = Z. | last7 = Xu | first7 = Z. | last8 = Wu | first8 = Y. | last9 = Huang | first9 = W. | last10 = Qian | first10 = P.-Y. | last11 = Zhang | first11 = X. X. | year = 2013 | title = Bio-Assembled Nanocomposites in Conch Shells Exhibit Giant Electret Hysteresis | url = | journal = Adv. Mater | volume = 25 | issue = | pages = 711–718 | doi = 10.1002/adma.201202079 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Polar bear fur has inspired the design of thermal collectors and clothing.&lt;ref&gt;http://rsta.royalsocietypublishing.org/content/367/1894/1749|Bionics in textiles: flexible and translucent thermal insulations for solar thermal applications|Published 29 March 2009 doi: 10.1098/rsta.2009.0019 Phil. Trans. R. Soc. A 13 May 2009 vol. 367 no. 1894 1749-1758&lt;/ref&gt; The [[phyllotaxy|arrangement of leaves on a plant]] has been adapted for better solar power collection.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.amnh.org/learn-teach/young-naturalist-awards/winning-essays2/2011-winning-essays/the-secret-of-the-fibonacci-sequence-in-trees |title=The Secret of the Fibonacci Sequence in Trees |work=2011 Winning Essays |publisher=[[American Museum of Natural History]] |date=1 May 2014 |accessdate=17 July 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; The light refractive properties of the moth's eye has been studied to reduce the reflectivity of solar panels.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author1=Wilson, S.J. Wilson |author2=Hutley, M.C. | title=The Optical Properties of 'Moth Eye' Antireflection Surfaces | journal=Journal of Modern Optics | volume=29 | issue=7 | pages=993–1009| year=1982 | doi=10.1080/713820946}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Self-healing material]]s, [[polymer]]s and [[composite material]]s capable of mending cracks have been produced based on biological materials.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|title=Self healing in polymers and polymer composites. Concepts, realization and outlook: A review |journal=Polymer Letters |year=2008 |volume=2 |pages=238–250 |doi=10.3144/expresspolymlett.2008.29 |author=Zang, M.Q.|issue=4}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Bombardier beetle]]'s powerful repellent spray inspired a Swedish company to develop a "micro mist" spray technology, which is claimed to have a low carbon impact (compared to aerosol sprays). The beetle mixes chemicals and releases its spray via a steerable nozzle at the end of its abdomen, stinging and confusing the victim.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.swedishbiomimetics.com/biomimetics_folder.pdf Swedish Biomimetics: The &amp;mu;Mist Platform Technology] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20131213022851/http://www.swedishbiomimetics.com/biomimetics_folder.pdf |date=December 13, 2013 }}. Retrieved 3 June 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;

Most [[virus]]es have an outer capsule 20 to 300&amp;nbsp;nm in diameter. Virus capsules are remarkably robust and capable of withstanding temperatures as high as 60&amp;nbsp;°C; they are stable across the [[pH]] range 2-10.&lt;ref name="Tong" /&gt; Viral capsules can be used to create nano device components such as nanowires, nanotubes, and quantum dots. Tubular virus particles such as the [[tobacco mosaic virus]] (TMV) can be used as templates to create nanofibers and nanotubes, since both the inner and outer layers of the virus are charged surfaces which can induce nucleation of crystal growth. This was demonstrated through the production of [[platinum]] and [[gold]] nanotubes using TMV as a template.&lt;ref name="Dujardin"&gt;Dujardin E., Peet C. "Nano Letters" 2003. 3:413.&lt;/ref&gt;  Mineralized virus particles have been shown to withstand various pH values by mineralizing the viruses with different materials such as silicon, [[Lead(II) sulfide|PbS]], and [[Cadmium sulfide|CdS]] and could therefore serve as a useful carriers of material.&lt;ref name="Shenton"&gt;Shenton W. Douglas, Young M. "Advanced Materials" 1999. 11:253.&lt;/ref&gt;  A spherical plant virus called [[cowpea chlorotic mottle virus]] (CCMV) has interesting expanding properties when exposed to environments of pH higher than 6.5.  Above this pH, 60 independent pores with diameters about 2&amp;nbsp;nm begin to exchange substance with the environment.  The structural transition of the viral capsid can be utilized in [[Biomineralization|Biomorphic mineralization]] for selective uptake and deposition of minerals by controlling the solution pH.  Possible applications include using the viral cage to produce uniformly shaped and sized quantum dot [[semiconductor]] nanoparticles through a series of pH washes.  This is an alternative to the [[Ferritin|apoferritin]] cage technique currently used to synthesize uniform CdSe nanoparticles.&lt;ref&gt;Ischiro Yamashita, Junko Hayashi, Mashahiko Hara. "Bio-template Synthesis of Uniform CdSe Nanoparticles Using Cage-shaped Protein, Apoferritin." Chemistry Letters (2004). Volume: 33, Issue: 9. 1158–1159.&lt;/ref&gt; Such materials could also be used for targeted drug delivery since particles release contents upon exposure to specific pH levels.

[[Surface tension biomimetics]] are being researched for technologies such as hydrophobic or hydrophilic coatings and microactuators.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Yuan|first1=Zhiqing|title=A novel fabrication of a superhydrophobic surface with highly similar hierarchical structure of the lotus leaf on a copper sheet|journal=Applied Surface Science|date=15 November 2013|volume=285|pages=205–210|doi=10.1016/j.apsusc.2013.08.037}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Huh|first1=Dongeun|title=Reconstituting Organ-Level Lung Functions on a Chip|journal=Science|date=25 June 2010|volume=328|issue=5986|pages=1662–1668|doi=10.1126/science.1188302|pmid=20576885}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Mayser|first1=Matthias|title=Layers of Air in the Water beneath the Floating Fern Salvinia are Exposed to Fluctuations in Pressure|journal=Integrative and Comparative Biology|date=12 June 2014|volume=56|issue=5|pages=1–7}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Borno|first1=Ruba|title=Transpiration actuation: the design, fabrication and characterization of biomimetic microactuators driven by the surface tension of water|journal=Journal of Micromechanics and Microengineering|date=21 September 2006|volume= 16|issue= 11|pages=2375–2383|doi=10.1088/0960-1317/16/11/018}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Garrod|first1=R.|title=Mimicking a Stenocara Beetle’s Back for Microcondensation Using Plasmachemical Patterned Superhydrophobic-Superhydrophilic Surfaces|journal=Langmuir|date=4 October 2006|volume= 23|issue= 2|pages=689–693|doi=10.1021/la0610856}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;!--do not add anything here without a citation – it will be removed--&gt;

== See also ==
{{Portal|Biotechnology}}
* [[Artificial photosynthesis]]
* [[Artificial enzyme]]
* [[Artificial enzyme#Nanozymes]]
* ''[[Bioinspiration &amp; Biomimetics]]''
* [[Biomimetic synthesis]]
* [[Neuromorphic computing]]
* [[Reverse engineering]]
* [[Synthetic biology]]
&lt;!--ONLY GENERAL, SOMEWHAT RELATED TOPICS HERE--&gt;
&lt;!--Please do not add links to individual implementations, robots, etc, as they will be removed. Add them with suitable descriptions and references in the main text.--&gt;

== References ==
{{reflist|28em}}

== Further reading ==

* Benyus, J. M. (2001). ''Along Came a Spider''. Sierra, 86(4), 46-47.
* Hargroves, K. D. &amp; Smith, M. H. (2006). ''Innovation inspired by nature Biomimicry''. Ecos, (129), 27-28.
* Marshall, A. (2009). ''Wild Design: The Ecomimicry Project'', North Atlantic Books: Berkeley.
* Passino, Kevin M. (2004). ''Biomimicry for Optimization, Control, and Automation.'' Springer.
* Pyper, W. (2006). ''Emulating nature: The rise of industrial ecology''. Ecos, (129), 22-26.
* Smith, J. (2007). ''It’s only natural''. The Ecologist, 37(8), 52-55.
* [[D'Arcy Wentworth Thompson|Thompson, D'Arcy W.]], ''On Growth and Form''. Dover 1992 reprint of 1942 2nd ed. (1st ed., 1917).
* [[Steven Vogel|Vogel, S.]] (2000). ''Cats' Paws and Catapults: Mechanical Worlds of Nature and People''.  Norton.

== External links ==
{{Prone to spam|date=December 2016}}
{{Z148}}&lt;!--     {{No more links}}

       Please be cautious adding more external links.

Wikipedia is not a collection of links and should not be used for advertising.

     Excessive or inappropriate links will be removed.

 See [[Wikipedia:External links]] and [[Wikipedia:Spam]] for details.

If there are already suitable links, propose additions or replacements on
the article's talk page, or submit your link to the relevant category at
DMOZ (dmoz.org) and link there using {{Dmoz}}.

--&gt;
* [https://www.youtube.com/user/MITbiomimetics Biomimetics MIT]
* [http://www.scribemedia.org/2008/10/22/float-like-a-butterfly-with-janine-benyus ''Sex, Velcro and Biomimicry'' with Janine Benyus]
* [http://www.ted.com/talks/janine_benyus_biomimicry_in_action.html Janine Benyus: Biomimicry in Action] from TED 2009
* [http://ngm.nationalgeographic.com/2008/04/biomimetics/clark-photography Design by Nature - National Geographic]
* [http://www.ted.com/talks/michael_pawlyn_using_nature_s_genius_in_architecture.html Michael Pawlyn: Using nature's genius in architecture] from TED 2010
* [http://www.ted.com/talks/robert_full_on_engineering_and_evolution.html Robert Full shows how human engineers can learn from animals' tricks] from TED 2002
* [http://arquivo.pt/wayback/20160518082206/http://www.eveningnews.com/blogs/2009/11/08/fastdraw/entry5577007.shtml ''The Fast Draw: Biomimicry''] from CBS News

{{Biotechnology}}

[[Category:Evolutionary biology]]
[[Category:Biotechnology]]
[[Category:Bioinformatics]]
[[Category:Biological engineering]]
[[Category:Biophysics]]
[[Category:Industrial ecology]]
[[Category:Bionics]]
[[Category:Water conservation]]
[[Category:Renewable energy]]
[[Category:Sustainable transport]]</text>
      <sha1>2phgl75jscax0d9ug5v320p4pyuyo97</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>